A Guide to the Papers of Henry James, 1855-1969, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
  - Two Men: A Novel by Elizabeth Stoddard by Henry James 1865, AMs, 23 pp. on 23 l. (Box-folder 1:17)
    - Henry James to Herbert Gilchrist, 1912 May 5, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 7:33)
      Come if he can. It will give James much pleasure. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Alice Stopfard] Green, 1912 May 20, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 7:34)
      How can he thank her for such a beautiful letter? If being daughter of Puritans doesn't sow the end of such impulses, and being a sister of the Amenities, does long live again that admirable and awful race. Thinks she put a splendid charity on his ill-starred Browning effort. Demoralized by delay before he got to his feet, and lost confidence and courage. Talks of her going to French coast, which she will have to explain as Mrs. [Mary] Ward explains Ulster. Wouldn't mind her being so backward if she wasn't by way of being so forward. His title for Book was unavailable, but second best has its beauty. In bound volume filed at 1888 January 28. #6251-a
    - [Henry James] to Alice [Gibbens] James, 1912 June 3, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:35)
      Blessed by her note. Deeply interested in her plans. Rejoices that she will come up on the 6th. If she comes up earlier in the day he could take her to two private views in the afternoon. Will take her on to a much more interesting one on Friday that will be very pleasant. She can wind up loose ends back at Lamb House. But he will hold fast to her until the last moment. He takes his honorary degree at Oxford on the 26th and will come back to town on the 27th at nearest. Her days will easily fill themselves at Lamb House. Will go with her to the Tower and to the House of Commons, everywhere, anywhere, but to dine at the Clarks and at the [Lee-Warners]! Could almost weep at her being reduced to the Society of the Marshalls. However, Kidd and Burgess and Jean will make up for them, I hope. Interesting letter from Harry (from Chocorua). There is a most distressing fact in it, that a very long letter that James wrote him never reached him. The explanation is with the tragic Titanic, although James didn't check the date, it must have been posted a fortnight before the Titanic. It's the only letter in all the years that he can remember losing, and it is rather miserable as it will be a difficult one to write over. If she comes on Thursday, won't be able to see her until the next day as he is dining out that night. But he will communicate early. #6251-av
    - Henry James to Ashley Dodd, 1912 July 30, TL, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 7:36)
      Interested in her reissue of her charming little yearbook, and in finding impression of her beautiful Godinton rise before him. Happy she thinks any words of his may help new volume. She can use his letter which he read over, as it stands, written after first publication of book. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1912 August 18, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:37)
      His clouds are very artful and beautiful, and his publication most elegant and charming. He has combined photography remarkably with aviation. A couple of his pictures could have been taken only from an "aeroplane." Understands his sense of exile at horribly cheerful, booming, luminous and barbaric Los Angeles; must be a long, drawn-out torture. Remembers how it struck him ten years ago as a cluster of the more ragged fringes and a strangle of deafening and death-dealing car tracks. Get out of it as soon as possible and wash his sore eyes in the balm of the Thames. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Ashley Dodd, 1912 September 8, TL, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 7:38)
      Returns proof with corrections in punctuation. Would rejoice in a copy of book with his tiny preface, which he hopes won't sink it, but rather float it. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Edmund] Gosse, 1912 October 7, TLS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:39)
      Dictated. He is a stricken man and still not on his legs. Has had a devil of a summer through renewal of ailment which he thought subdued: chronic anginal pain. Got better but was smitten with atrocious affliction of "Shingles." Concluded agreement for London flat. Will winter there and spend rest of his days there. Proprietors want a "social reference" so he has given Gosse's distinguished name as a voucher for his respectability. Will take flat December 25. Waiting for new volume of his Dictionary, with his Swinburne. #6251-m
    - Henry James to [Edmund] Gosse, 1912 October 10, TLS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:40)
      Dictated. His letter consoles and sustains him. Lessars won't apply for character reference if hasn't done so yet. Received Swinburne with pleasure. Discusses book and criticizes it. Has received two of dear old Meredith's letters. Must discuss them, and Wells' book with which he is having extreme difficulty. What lacerates him is meanness and poorness of editing. Must be at it again. #6251-m
    - Henry James to [Edmund] Gosse, 1912 October 11, TLS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:41)
      Dictated. Thanks him for helping him with fastidious friends of the flat. Interesting note regarding George Meredith. Agrees with his judgment of their marked non-illustration of his intellectual wealth. They make one enormously like him. The whole case is full of anomalies, and these volumes illustrate it. He was starved in many ways, and that makes him more nobly pathetic. Gives own account of his intercourse with Meredith. James slowly mending. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Alice and Bill [William James, Jr.], 1912 October 12-15, TL, 16 pp. on 16 l. with envelope; signature cut. (Box-folder 7:42)
      Dictated. Forgive this brutal machinery to which he is reduced if he can't delay in responding. Just over a violent and detestable attack of the "Shingles." Letters have piled up. Pain extremely excruciating. Asks Bill if his father suffered from this condition? Or was it you? Remembers his mother nursing one of them. Very dismal because it came upon him when he just got over another illness. Months have not been happy for him. The poisonously cold and wet summer may must have been responsible for his condition. His staff has been ministering angels. Fanny Prothero has been often by his bedside, discussing Alice a lot. Remembers, before his illness, a number of sweet September afternoon turns with Fanny P. all over the countryside: very refreshing and interesting, and always, on the part of those ladies, inquiries and ravings about you. Will be moving to two delightful and sufficiently spacious rooms where he will be able to put up his three servants commodiously enough. October 13: Had to break off letter yesterday. Feels that when he is over this sickness he will be fitter than at any time for ever and ever so long past. Tell Aleck thanks for his beautiful letter. Obtained in London the very good photograph of the Robert Allerton head and that two copies of the same went to Monticello, Illinois. Discussed difficulty in sending previous photographs. Writes about the recent tragedy of the wicked old Brede: little Ghita Stanhope, a friend of Clare Sheridan's, "blew her brains out, in the most gruesome way" some six weeks ago. She was frankly demented. She struck me as the most charming young thing conceivable. October 15: Again had to break off letter. Relapsed again. Lamb House is a good place to be ill, being so honest and true a little nook. Yearns over Peg to the fullest extent. Envies her sinking so deep into Mamma's so deeply sweet hospitality. Send news of Harry's great visions and echoes in New York. #6251-av
    - Henry James to [Edmund] Gosse, 1912 October 13, TLS, 5 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:43)
      Dictated. Protests his imputation of sarcasm in his letter. More discussion of George Meredith's Letters and admiration of Daudets' Numa Roumestan. James impressed by non-occurrence of Balzac's name. James still on shaky ground physically; has had many relapses and returns to bed. #6251-m
    - Henry James to [Edmund] Gosse, 1912 October 15, TLS, 4 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:44)
      Dictated. Sympathy to his wife for loss of brother. So it goes, until one has no one left, as he felt two years ago, when he lost his last two brothers and became sole survivor in family. Comments on beautifully done Swinburne chapter in Cornhill in detail and gives own memories of meetings with Flaubert, Richard Burton, et al. Interested in his echo of Haldane's remarks regarding George Meredith. Meredith was an admirable spirit, if not an entire mind; he throws out splendid moral and ethical "spiritual" lights. Trying to keep mainly out of bed again. #6251-m
    - Henry James to Mary Ward, 1912 October 22, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:45)
      Dictated. Has been laid up 3 weeks with "shingles." Still most sorry, but is working off some correspondence. Can make no social adventure. He feels chapter of "social adventure" forever closed and he must go on for the rest of his days at home. He is aged, infirm, unsociable, and detached in the political game which forms the constant carnival for young people. Has view of coming to town after Christmas, and reserves the social adventure of tea at Grosvenor Place as the highest crown of his confidence. Glad she has finished a gallant piece of work. More than he can say for himself after a summer of stiff frustration. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mary Ward, 1912 October 24, TLS, 4 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:46)
      Dictated. Thanks her for expression of kindness. Doing his utmost to get better. Yearns when he thinks of the balm of talking with her. Wrote to H. G. Wells who sent him "Marriage," but would rather have written her. With him he felt irrelevant and vain and ineffectual. Strange, in his affair, the coexistence of so much talent with so little art, so much life with so little living! Thinks him more interesting by his faults than he will probably manage to be in any other way, and he is a vivid and violent object lesson. Envies her the jollity of having polished off a brilliant coup and celebrating the case in Paris. Enter into a relationship with Mrs. [Edith] Wharton, if convenient, if she is back from the last of her dazzling braveries of her far excursionism. She may be able to appease his always lively appetite for news of her. Don't acknowledge this letter in any manner with all else she has to do. Talks of young people vs. aged and infirm. Asks her not to pity him his dim exclusion; the past words seem to him the very measure of intellectual insipidity, rather than representing the "salt-of-life" as she put it. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1912 November 10, TLS, 5 pp. on 5 l. (Box-folder 7:47)
      Dictated. So unwell he must dictate. Longed for news of him. Had very bad summer with dreadful pain from shingles. Rejoices in his fine air of prosperity and success. Still hopes to meet. #6251
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1912 November 28, TLS, 4 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:48)
      Dictated. His dream touches him more than he can say, but what he doesn't see is the application of the vast puzzle, or the steps to convert it into reality. Dousing him with cold water again when he only meant to spray him and his sublime good faith and his splendid imagination. Abominable shingles have been known to last three months, and he is a three month case and curiosity. #6251
    - Henry James to Alice [Gibbens] James, 1913 February 4-5, TLS, 9 pp. on 9 l. (Box-folder 7:49)
      Dictated. In dismal arrears with Bill and Alice, but responds to their letter. The days are better for him. The move to town has been very helpful, and his situation couldn't be better. Jane and Wilfrid and Emily Sargent are the fondest, faithfullest little neighbors. Kidd came back in rapture at being restored. Kidd is really a heroine, of judgment as well as devotion. Please keep an eye on her in respect to the eventual future. Most importantly, James takes great pleasure in their present turn of life. Glad he was in Boston recently, as it helped James see and feel their condition. February 5: Had to break off letter yesterday. Forgive him. Still recovering from sickness which has been sticking to him like a poisonous plaster. Dr. Wheeler continues to help, though he has seen rather remarkably few doctors. Many specifics about James's sickness, but tells them not to worry. Happy to hear that his blest Aleck will be sailing to see him June 10th. Bill and Alice must be the most howling social successes that Boston has ever known. Wishes he could be there to show how howling the old uncle finds them. Discusses work on his sitting-room walls by Earnest von Glehn. #6251-av
    - Henry James to Mary Ward, 1913 February 20, TLS, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:50)
      Dictated. Thanks her for finding time to write, in her crowded and complicated life. He has had to give himself up to having a sudden ailment looked after, which is being successfully done. Glad she has been kind to Hugh Walpole, on whom nothing good or fine is wasted. He is a valued, young friend and he cherishes him. Egging her on to read Fortitude is another matter. It's doing well may not be an enlightening thing for him. Hasn't been to Paris in five years. Would rather go to Hoxton to hear Chevrillon on Galsworthy. To hear it rubbed in would be the end of all things. He took his paper in the Revuee for a strange and cruel practical joke, or a piece of macabre irony. When the French are bêtes, they bring to their bêtise the same perfection they bring to everything. Envies her the luxury of her mornings of perusal. P.S. Should be delighted to see her there if she found the pilgrimage convenient. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1913 March 5, ALS, 6 pp on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:51)
      Silent because endlessly ill and unable to write. Upset at his ghastly question as to whether he is offended with him. More than he can bear. Illness since 1910 is something he has not recovered from and never shall. #6251
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1913 March 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 7:52)
      Appreciates his generous letters. James's travel powers of every sort is dead and finished. Hopes he will come in his young might to England, and they will embrace over the abyss of their differences in years and conditions. Greatly rejoices in his, and bears his own really quite well. #6251
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1913 March 25, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:53)
      Touched by his tender participation, but must not think of him now, for James has a compromised life as one may well have at his age. Doesn't miss his freedom of range if he can only stay as he is. Just received the splendid printed sheets from him. Pleads with him against a size of page that defies human handling: people won't read what they can't, such as the huge folios. It is very handsome, but judges expensive. Pardon his depressed tone, but he can't leap and bound. #6251
    - "Friends and Admirers" to Henry James, 1913 April 15, photocopy, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:54)
      Happy returns of the day; when he reads their names he will see they represent many different degrees of association with him. Old friends and new friends attached to him by long standing intimacy and affection. They all love and honor him, and welcome the opportunity of telling him with one voice. He is the writer, the master of rare and beautiful art, in whose work creation and criticism meet as they have never before met in our language. Their sense of the genius by which a power so original is brought under the ancient discipline of art is expressly offered symbol of The Golden Bowl. He is also the friend they know and love. Another present they wish to give him; let one of them paint his portrait, and accept it as a gift to him and to the country in which he has made his home. Photocopy of a group letter sent to Henry James on his birthday signed by "Friends and Admirers" which includes approximately 242 names. In bound volume filed at 1888 January 28. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 April 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:55)
      Dictated. Silent because he has had a winter of unwellness. Now consists on taking self for better, and wants to see his great works and their author. #6251-g
    - Henry James to "Dear Friends All," 1913 April 21, photocopy, 4 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:56)
      Acknowledges with boundless pleasure the beautiful letter for his birthday. Emotion is too deep for stammering words. Was drawn to London long years ago, and now sees his faith was to sink deeper foundations. Makes him feel highly successful and extremely proud. Pays best respects for 250 pairs of hands and the inestimable bowl which he will admire as he sits for his friend Sargent. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 April 29, TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:57)
      His offer regarding Paris very handsome, but of no use to him. Suggests possible photographs. Wishes he had got him to do vast New York sky-scraper hotel. Maybe he has such among his New York images. Enjoy himself, and James will come on his return, and profit from his California harvest. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 May 2, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:58)
      Dictated. Thinks view from Montmartre will do for The Velvet Glove. Glad of his good report of his doings. Keep it up to the bitter end. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower, 1913 May 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 7:59)
      Kind note, but if she knew how little his going out consorts with his state. Evenings out have been at an end for a long time. May he come to tea with her? #6251-a
    - Henry James to Mrs. [Juliet] Trower, 1913 May 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 7:60)
      Will come Saturday, June 7 at 5:15 for tea with great pleasure. #6251-a
    - Henry James to [Mrs. Daniel Sargent Curtis], 1913 June 14, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. (Box-folder 7:61)
      Filled with horror at not writing. Glad to have news of their adventures from Mrs. [Mary] Hunter. Saw her at one of his sittings with [John Singer] Sargent for his portrait. It is almost finished, and he is almost sorry, as studio visits are so delightful. Will be there until July and then back to Rye. Glad to have small home in town. Glad to see Jessie Allen for news of them and to see she has recuperated. Thanks Mrs. Curtis for appreciation of his too fat book. Thrilling that she saw Napoleon borne to Invalides. James doing second installment of the book, and they shall have to talk about it soon. Hopes Ralph Latimer comes with her. #6251-ag
    - Henry James to R[obert] U[nderwood] Johnson, 1913 June 17, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 7:62)
      Dictated. Writes regarding the candidates for the election into the Academy, but James must be writing after the election. Should have voted for W. R. Thayer, and even with his information about Cole and Gilbert, James still feels pure helplessness for the candidacy. Vote for any painter, sculptor, architect or musical composer as to whom James definitely commanded, not say "properly instructed," because he doesn't hold that in any summary fashion one can be! P.S. Gives in to temptation to send two enclosed documents [not present] to show how handsomely a member of our body is capable of being treated "over here." It has given him much pleasure. #6251-as
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 June 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:63)
      Dictated. He is ill all the time; he has a grave chronic ailment. Cannot make or take off-hand engagements. Handicapped in correspondence, too. Some he never answers at all. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 June 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:64)
      Dictated. Cannot come Friday, but Saturday if it suits him. Exempt from impediments. P.S. Will bring old daguerreotype of his uncle, which he said he would be able to photograph. #6251-g
    - Henry James to Hendrik [Christian Anderson], 1913 September 4, ALS, 8 pp. on 4 l. (Box-folder 7:65)
      Distress and embarrassment have kept him silent. Forced to speak of certain matters. Anderson had written of plans for World Centre and sent first installment of his pamphlet World conscience. He appears to have forgotten the impression James tried to give. Does he think James likes to tell him he doesn't and can't go with him, congratulate him, or understand his projects and plans so vast and vague and meaningless to him? He takes so much for granted. Left so short a time ago Roman studio and statues, interesting and limited if a little alarming in scale and number. Can only give James pain to be forced to give criticism on what he can't understand: Anderson's term "world" and his vain and false presumptions seem to James nothing. They would seem so if James were not old and ill and detached, and reduced to ending his life in restricted ways. Loathes such pretensions of "world" anything. Can't sympathize or support Anderson's proposals. Must cultivate his garden morally and intellectually. Anderson must recover the proportions of things; the way he is following Megalomania is leading to madness. They can talk if Anderson sees reality, things as they are. #6251-a
    - Henry James to Alvin [Langdon Coburn], 1913 September 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with envelope. (Box-folder 7:66)
      Applauds his show at a distance as James is unable to go and come nowadays between Rye and London. Will return to London for winter on December 15. Afraid his exhibition will be over. Isn't Anderson having it in an empty London? May his show greatly prosper. Will see him privately. Hasn't seen Androcles, but it will probably run until he can see it. #6251-g
    - [Henry James] to Bill [William James, Jr.], 1913 September 28, ALS, 10 pp. on 5 l. with typed transcript. (Box-folder 7:67)
      Thanks him for his splendid letter. His letter a great joy because of the vivid images and accounts of the blest little sub-nephew, or indeed super-nephew, and the authentic report of his work. Alice's photographs of the infant are intoxicating. Envious of Peg, who has gone home to see the infant in the flesh, in which she may bury an affectionate nose, what flesh, what proportions, and above all what a beautiful and incomparable head. Keep sending photographs. Peg's departure has been a true and great loss to him. Enjoys that she clearly likes dear old England. Lamb House has never been sweeter, and now it has been a most perfect September he has ever seen. Old Protheros and Fanny are still at Lamb House, though they depart shortly. Wishes he could find a quiet pair of tenants for Lamb House during the seven months he will be in town. If they know of anyone, please pass them along. Discusses Aleck growing up, although wonderstruck at his being able to stand the Thayer madhouse. James lies awake nights thinking of Aleck, and would pay more for a squint of something he has done than for a ticket for the Russian ballet. Asks Bill to treat his picture not as an Experiment, but only and ever as a production and a performance that he needs to be absolutely committed to, and then work out the given wrongness as much as he likes. But to no given wrongness should he ever sacrifice any saving rightness, that time! Treat every time now as the right time, for finish! But on that basis do anything and everything that will help him finish. Sorry about the non-success of the Kitty Emmet portrait. Alice will have a letter all to herself. #6251-aw
    - Henry James to [Joseph] Conrad, 1913 October 13, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 7:68)